software engineering radio episode 36
interview with guy Steele
welcome this is another episode of
software engineering radio today we have
an interview episode with guy Steele guy
works as a research for Sun Microsystems
labs and he's mainly involved in
programming language research you
probably know his name he has been
working quite a bit on Lisp he is the
author of the Common Lisp language
reference manual he's also worked on
Fortran so he's really an authority in
the programming language design area and
in this interview we talked about his
new project the fortress language we
have recorded this interview at the Chou
conference in October 2006 in Denmark
that's also why you can hear some
background noise from the exhibition
area of the conference but it's still
quite good quality have fun with the
interview and we're really pleased to
have guy on the podcast maybe we start
by introducing by you introducing
yourself a little bit and telling us
what you're doing where you're working
and what your background is in
programming language design obviously
all right right now I'm working at Sun
Microsystems at the research laboratory
the division on the east coast of the
United States in Burlington
Massachusetts I run a group called the
programming language research group of
that laboratory and right now we're
working on a new programming language
called fortress which is intended to be
a programming language for high-end
scientific computing ok and this is also
going to going to be the topic of the
talk of this discussion but maybe
briefly let's take a look into your
history you've been working quite a bit
with Lisp I guess and scheme right I
have I learned Lisp in 1970 that's been
36 years now I first became fascinated
with programming languages when I was
aged 14 and there is a computer at the
school I was attending Boston Latin
School and an alumnus who was an
executive at IBM and made sure the
school had an IBM 1130 which was a 16
mini computer and it ran Fortran have a
Fortran compiler so I learned to program
in Fortran
shortly after that I learned some other
programming languages including APL
which became an IBM product in 1969 the
next year it was announced at the spring
joint computer conference which happened
to be held in Boston and I even though I
was 15 years old I attended exhibits
area the conference and was fascinated
by the IBM booth by the super gaming
line which I was a geek it's true uh I
remember one time from that period when
I was walking around with a friend in
downtown Boston and some teenage girls
passed us in the other direction and I
knew they were looking at me because as
they passed one of them said wow did you
see all the pens in his pocket those
were the days of pocket protectors and
pens in the pocket and I was a geek so
one last question on this Lisp thing
today some of the concepts in Lisp are
kind of revived in other languages like
Ruby like the meta programming stuff or
something do you think there is some
kind of resurgence of some of this
dynamically typed and and meta
programming oriented programming
language thing yeah I think there is a
resurgence but I think they're just some
basic ideas that they got right and
lists that that people are constantly
rediscovering are useful good ideas the
idea of automatic storage management of
the garbage collector was a good idea
and the idea of having a way to
represent programs as data in a better
way than a string it was a good idea
yeah and it's it's that second idea that
makes the matter program something so
much easier in Lisp in such languages No
ok so that's let's switch over to your
current project the fortress language
can you outline what the goals of this
language are why do we need a new
language is probably the classical
question well we would like to do for
the Fortran community what Java did for
the C community and in fact the people
in the sign of community came to me
shortly after Java came out and said
Java has some wonderful features but
it's not quite adequate for our purposes
could you please extend Java so it's
more like Fortran and then we can have
the benefits of Internet programming
downloading code to web browsers and
stuff like that
and in fact there were some proposals
put through the Java community process
to make Java more suitable for the
scientific programmers and they were not
passed and I I was disappointed at the
time I think I realized that the needs
of scientific programmers are very
different from the needs of commercial
Internet programmers
and making the language better for one
community might make it worse for
another yeah so the Java community
process I think reacted correctly for
its community and said no we like Java
the way it is with respect to those
changes
yeah but there was still this need in
the scientific community for a safer
code easier to program code libraries
that can talk to the Internet
and when the opportunity came along to
do a new computer system design for as
part of a DARPA contract we decided to
tackle the programming language question
as a part of that mm-hmm that contract
as we started doing research and we said
what can we do for the Fortran community
now to make their lives easier and we
started instead of just starting with
Fortran and making it more Java we're
starting with Java and make more Fortran
like yeah we decided to start from
scratch and and do a requirements
analysis and forretress came out of that
and to give us a first overview what are
some of the you know in one 10 sentence
or two what are some of the most
important features that are actually
necessary for the scientific community
that distinguishes it from Java say
first of all they need an appropriate
set of data types and operations for
them they work a lot with floating-point
numbers Java actually has a very limited
set of floating-point operations they
need higher-level mathematical
abstractions particularly vectors and
matrices they need
ways of dealing with data structures
that operate at multiple levels of
resolution when you're doing physical
simulations there are places in the
physical simulation where there's a lot
of physical activity yeah and you need a
very fine grid for doing those
simulations in other parts not much is
going on the wind isn't blowing the the
Sun isn't shining and you don't need to
assign so many processors there you
don't need to allocate so much data
there yeah and so there are these very
elaborate things they've programmed with
great difficulty in Fortran so called
multi grid structures and better support
for that kind of thing would be useful
yeah and finally we wanted to provide a
better notation for them they are used
to working with a mathematical notation
we thought that we could bring the
programming language closer to what they
write on the whiteboard or in their
papers so for example you'd write papers
instead of reams yeah instead of using
an asterisk for multiplication just
write nothing yes for example blank yes
they're not used to writing asterisks in
fact asterisk usually means something
else didn't like information conjugate
of a matrix you know and little
notational things can make a big
difference to a programmer if you can
make it in some ways we're trying to
make a domain-specific language for
scientists yeah mm-hmm
so I read in one of the presentations I
saw about this topic that you don't try
to build the language or design it by
committee but rather try to grow it what
does that mean growing a language it
means that programming languages are
very complicated and you can't build it
all at once it's going to take time you
know Java has grown over time yeah and I
don't think that James Gosling
envisioned would Java would look like in
the year 2006 back when he was doing it
in 1994 yes yeah and so every
programming language has grown over time
we asked ourselves the question if we
know that the programming language is
going to grow and we want to support
that growth what technical changes would
we make to the language to make that
growth easier yeah and so if we plan for
growth we thought that might change the
way we design the language so that and
it has to some extent
and we'll talk about that later and that
could for example be that you have many
features in libraries instead of
hard-coded s in the language stuff yes
so do you think there there are there's
a risk to this approach because you
might compromise you know the the
coherence or the the uniformity of the
language concepts or didn't that turn
out to be a problem yet or no on the
country I think it is a big risk okay
yes we risk losing the cook the
coherency of the design yeah I think one
of the reasons that Java turned out to
be a coherent design is that one guy was
in charge of it I was like yeah and a
lot of the really good programming
languages at the beginning were yeah
maybe not the inventions of one guy but
one guy made the decision yeah as that
this fits and this doesn't fit my vision
of a language yeah whereas with
programming languages designed by
committee
you got a larger set of useful features
for the features them didn't always fit
together in the right ways No
so let's I guess that of course I know
because they're at the heights but so I
guess that one important feature for
this language is kind of primitive or
built-in support for parallelize
parallelism concurrency is an obvious
important thing so can you talk about
maybe about atomicity versus default
parallelism and also maybe talk about
some of the influences I could imagine
that outcome for example had some
influences on on the design of fortress
at this point or yes quite a bit as we
design or parallel constructs I actually
considered borrowing the seek and power
constructs from alchemy and then we
thought no that actually puts sequential
ISM and parallelism on an equal footing
and we really want to bias it for
parallels okay yeah and so we came up
with a a do loop syntax that is by
default parallel and you have we
purposely make you pay a syntactic tax
mm-hmm to get a sequential program and
that's an experiment we'll see whether
programmers like it what kinds of other
low level of first level support things
are there for parallelism at the lowest
level you can actually create a new
thread just the same way you say new
thread in Java yeah and that is a very
general mechanism it's sometimes hard
for compiler to optimize yeah but it is
completely general and we view that as a
tool for library writers to use to
make parallel abstractions there's
another low-level construct and language
which is simply that if you put two
expressions between parenthesis and put
a comma between they get evaluated in
parallel so this means the arguments to
a function can be evaluated in parallel
for example so it's funny because the
comma is usually the sequencing operator
and it's the parallelism operator in
that's a kind of a funny joke yeah
however semicolon is still sequencing it
okay I always use the semicolon here
I mentioned this before you said that
you'd like to have as many features as
possible as part of libraries instead of
the language core and also you talked
about syntax extension or being able to
add like mathematically looking syntax
to the language how do you handle syntax
extension through libraries or maybe
rephrasing the question how far can you
extend the syntax you probably know
about the IP project or intentional
software where I can project a program
to anything so how far do you do you go
with this with a syntax sugaring or
whatever you call this well it turns out
that a lot of mathematical syntax
actually falls into one of five or six
standard patterns you've got things that
are subscript that are super scripted
we've got in fix and prefix and postfix
operators you have things like big Sigma
that add up a bunch of values you
evaluate an expression many times and
those caps are about 90% of the notation
and so by providing those as standard
patterns and allowing the library to
define the semantics of an operator that
part of the syntax is actually kind of
built-in but then there's a separate
syntactic extension mechanism for the
patterns that don't fit those cases
mm-hm
and and I guess also that one of the
reasons that you tackle this
mathematical notation problem these days
is that you have Unicode so you have
more than 256 characters you can use in
your program like the 29 kinds of
parentheses you talked about I think yes
that's right Unicode is 20 in that 29
kinds of parentheses there will probably
be more coming I don't think you want to
use all 29 in one program but it's but
having perhaps six or eight kinds
instead of the three you have an ASCII
okay
can make a program more expressive yeah
so how does this library based language
extension thing influence the potential
for optimization how much compile
optimization can there be if stuff is
contributed through libraries is this I
mean it's certainly a concern in this
kind of language so well first of all
the compiler the poor compiler will need
to know a lot about optimizing method
calls and function calls and we are
assuming the kinds of optimizations you
see in hotspot compilers now for being
able to do both static and dynamic
prediction of which method is the most
likely one in an overloaded dispatch
that kind of thing but the other thing
is we expect to do some of the
traditional compiler optimizations at
the library level a lot of the knowledge
that's built into a compilers code
generator can be expressed if you have a
rich enough type system and by doing
polymorphic method dispatch in effect
you can do code selection and express
code selectors at the library level
mm-hmm so it's not something that that
kind of conflicts it's the optimization
thing doesn't conflict the library based
approach yes so we didn't mention that
before but I take it that that fortress
code will also run on some kind of VM
maybe even over the Java VM or or is it
natively compiled right now we have
implemented a toy interpreter this is
sort of a standard first step I got an
experimental language you will then work
on a compiler okay so the initial
interpreters written in Java and so it
will anywhere you can run a java virtual
machine you can run this interpreter
nice the next step will be to target a
compiler at JVM bytecode x' yeah and
then the third step will be to build a
customized VM for forretress yeah okay
and you talked about again mentioned it
a couple of times now about the ability
to extend the language through libraries
but I still guess you'll have a big set
of standard libraries so that you that
there is yeah a significant a big enough
set of stuff that people can rely on
that's existing that's right it's our
intention to to make fortress the open
source and that's one reason we want to
emphasize library approach because that
makes it easier for third parties to
participate
but a big mistake is to say oh it's open
source therefore other people will do
the job and we don't have to do ya know
we will provide a full standard library
and we will organize it into modules
it's important that the standard library
not be monolithic and what we will
divide it up the components in fact
there is a there are features for
component management in the fortress
language which we're going to talk about
yeah so that the type system is quite
interesting I thought because it's it is
a statically typed language yeah right
it's a strongly statically typed
language the type system is fairly
complicated because we want to be able
to describe complicated relationships
among data structures at compile time
mm-hmm but you still use type inference
so you don't have to ride down the type
everywhere just like c-sharp 3-0 I think
does it that's right what one thing we
noticed when watching scientists write
on whiteboards you know the sketching
out their algorithms is they don't write
down the types
you've got the types in their head yeah
for the most part and they tend to write
things like x equals y squared and
sometimes they mean that that they're
testing whether x equals y squared but
more often they just mean let X equal Y
squared and they don't bother right the
type of X because it's the same as the
type of Y squared hmm yeah so that's a
simple example type inference and when
you have a simple equality like that but
there are a lot of other situations
where the types can be correctly
implicitly inferred there's only one
type and why make the programmer write
it down everywhere when it only clutters
is thinking yeah if he wants to write it
explicitly he can yeah yeah that makes
makes a lot of sense yeah so let's talk
a bit more about some of the type system
details while preparing this this
discussion I obviously looked at some
material off the faultless language and
there are a couple of things I found
interesting you talked about traits
using traits instead of classical
multiple inheritance I guess yes or
instead of using implementation
inheritance and you also mentioned that
there is some support for automated or
integrated unit testing as part of the
type system and that's very interesting
so please elaborate on these kinds of a
little bit all right well a trait in the
fortress language the idea of trait was
borrowed for some work that's done in
the small talk community mm-hm
and at rate you can think of as a Java
interface except it can have code in it
it's not a mixin it's sort of like a
mixin yes so so a trait can inherit from
several other traits and objects can
inherit from traits and you can inherit
not only code but also testing
information and contract information so
one can put contracts on methods that
that describe how they are intended to
behave contracts in the sense of I saw
mile yeah okay mines at the Eiffel line
edge okay programming my contract yes
okay in addition you can also specify
invariants on traits and on data
structures so you can say for example
for this kind of number addition is
commutative and associative and
multiplication is associative or not
commutative as with make matrices and
you can also specify test data mm-hmm
that is example data on which these
properties are to be checked mm-hmm and
then the testing system takes it from
there and automatically generates
testing code that will make sure the
properties are satisfied by the test
data and NL porters and the test system
is obviously not part of the language
but it's a separate thing I guess but
the fact that you can embed the test
data in the languages of course the
language feature yes okay so do you
think and we're going to talk talk about
another feature that fits in this
category this is actually not just
interesting fossil scientists so also
you optimize this language for a
scientific background I think it's it's
at least it sounds also interesting for
general-purpose programming certainly a
side effect you you you you're happy
about right so yes well I hope there
will be you are it helps when designing
language to have a particular app user
community be your focus yes because
because it keeps your design focused
yeah but we do have some hope that some
of the technologies we develop may prove
to be useful in the java community and
and in other language communities we're
not out to replace java but that would
have been my next question yes but but
but we are out to explore some
interesting and risky new language
technology and the ones that turn out to
work may be borrowed yeah so another
thing I really loved about this the
stuff I read about the language is
this notion of components where you can
explicitly import and export my facets
or ports or interfaces or what have you
call this why why did you I mean why did
you put this into the language as a
first-class feature because that's
something I've never seen before and
this in this way in languages for a
couple of reasons one is that we wanted
to think explicitly about the management
of segments of the language as part of
the growing a language story and we
think that a part of being able to grow
a language is to be able to replace old
parts as well as add new ins and for
that you need component management with
version control you'll be able to be
able to divide your standard library
into manageable pieces yeah and the
other is that we want to do have
programmed control over how programs are
built from smaller pieces mm-hmm so you
can actually write executable code that
will govern how components are
constructed and built so think to think
in effect think of make as being part of
the language okay mm-hmm and you can
also build hierarchical components you
can assemble components from I guess
component instances of other types yes
exactly because this is exactly what for
example the embedded folks do quite a
lot in the room methodology or even you
put UML 2.0 so I and it's also stuff
that I use a lot as the guiding metaphor
if I do architectural stuff so having
this as part of the language I think is
from my point of view it's maybe even
the biggest contribution of this
language so I really think this is
really cool thank you another term that
I found in this context is API is how
are they different from interfaces or
what is an API I mean in the context of
Patras an interface describes one
particular data structure whereas an API
can describe a set of data structures a
set of function and Method interfaces
also how they collaborate may be and how
to collaborate yes and another
difference is that
api's are constrained not to have code
in them unlike the traits which do
mm-hmm
one exceptions the api's can have
testing code that make sense so let's
again revisit this this parallelism
and concurrency stuff there is probably
some specific support for distribution
and and to being able to to distribute
different parts of an algorithm onto
different nodes machines processors what
are the primitives that you provide
there well the lowest level primitives
that we expect we used by the library
writers are the ability to spawn a
thread and say where that thread should
be spawned so there is a description of
the Machine structure as part of the
language as part of a language and in
previous languages such as MPI about the
only machine description is how many
processors do you have we defined a
fairly elaborate data structure that can
capture a lot of the properties of
machine including how many processors
how many memories which is not
necessarily the same as number of
processors are the processors bundled
into cores how is storage allocated
because the heap that is used by a
storage allocation may be divided into
segments those segments may or may not
correspond to Hardware memories mm-hmm
so all of these properties of processors
memories are described by this data
structure and by studying this data
structure a program can figure out at
runtime how what is the best way to
organize the distribution of an array on
the machine player distribution of
threads they are saying instead of like
knowing at the time of writing the
program how the Machine structure would
look like and hop coding this into the
into the program and saying that there
is this kind of reflective feature about
the machine and the program can optimize
itself or distribute its load depending
on where it's running at this time
exactly on the other hand you don't want
the overhead of doing that every time
you distribute an array right so there's
actually one a layer of indirection from
regions one in effect pre-compile
something called a distribution which is
the description of that mapping mm-hm so
you pre compile that distribution once
and then the distribution is then in
effect a little piece of code that knows
how to map any given size array onto
that machine although this is code
to compile optimization at this point
it's important yes but but that's the
structure we put in fact that structure
something the compiler doesn't know
about that's that's an aspect of our
current design for the standard library
right and if someone figures out a
better way of doing that precompilation
replace the library
are you considering to put in specific
support for like real-time or embedded
programming like for example the ability
to have deadlines on the execution time
budgets on the execution of of a method
or something because it sounds like it
would be a related topic it sounds like
a great topic that's something we
haven't addressed yet just because
that's not our chosen target audience
initially and that's done something we'd
love to get into eventually but we have
to pick our battles yeah there any time
frame until when I mean can people
download the language and and and how to
sauce the the the roadmap now yeah at
present we have a toy interpreter
working internally in the laboratory and
it's about 2/3 implemented you know
they're they're places where you put in
a certain kind of program we'll say oh
that feature isn't implemented yeah when
we get it sufficiently complete and
robust enough then we plan first of all
to probably put it up on our website so
people can type fortress programs into a
webpage and have them evaluated mm-hmm
then at a later stage we will release
the interpreter code itself probably you
know we hoped open-source it would first
we need to work out the legal details of
starting an open-source community for
fortress
yeah as soon so it's coming from sun i'd
guess it's going to be open source just
like everything else
yes one thing I was interested in and
maybe two to wrap up this session I've
seen all these slides and they contain
an awful lot of Patras code obviously
yeah so have you have you been writing
this code before we actually had the
interpreter or did you do this in
parallel so I was wondering how you can
come up with these huge amounts of
slides with probably correct right the
fortress code without having the
language implemented well I'm not sure I
can guarantee it's correct until I
actually execute it and even the
execution is no guarantee of course but
yes we have we have been doing writing a
lot of code on paper you know as part of
the design process you know just as an
architect as sketches and builds models
yeah
but we also run some of these codes
through the interpreter and it's an
iterative process we write programs and
we write the interpreter and we do the
two together and how do you interact
with your potential customers the
scientists are the scientists on the
team or are you scientists and have this
background or how no I'm not a scientist
I'm a wannabe scientist I love science
scientists and scientific work I studied
physics in college yeah but no we've
been working with representatives from
mostly the United States National
Laboratories as well as some
universities and as a part of our DARPA
contract which is funding some of this
work we have a three day review every
six months as well as email contact in
between and they often suggest kernel
benchmarks that they will bring us a
piece of Fortran code and say what is
this look like in fortress okay anything
else you want to say about fortress
anything I forgot to ask obviously
there's a lot of stuff we can't cover
but I guess the main thing I'd like to
say is that while I have been the
spokesperson for fortress at this
conference it is actually a team of
eight to ten persons there's been
working on it and I want to thank that
team because they have provided a lot of
contributions yeah and I would not have
been able to yeah and we hope to open it
up and get even more of the world
involved in our team no okay guys thanks
you very much for being on the show it
was really interesting as usual the
language sessions as I think our most
interesting ones Thanks thank you very
much
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - Radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Cowley for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details